本字幕由大家字幕组 原创翻译制作
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
若因私自散布传播造成法律问题 本字幕组概不负责更多影视请搜索并关注新浪微博 大家字幕组
翻译： 翻译一集要吃好多肉的肉肉  Cindy  星星美少女
翻译：小俊仔儿  汉谟拉  抹茶苏  小小_鱼
时间轴：静宇  Sandra 压制：太阳雨  校对：翻译一集要吃好多肉的肉肉
公元1529年 由于英王亨利八世及其妻子-
西班牙公主阿拉贡的凯瑟琳王后 结婚20年
仍无男性子嗣继承王位 故英王在2年前
已向教皇提出了离婚请求 至今未果
【 因根据当时的天主教教规 夫妻结合是上帝的旨意 离婚、丧偶再嫁娶 需要教皇的批准 】
红衣主教、大法官、也是亨利八世的忠实拥护者 托马斯・沃尔西在这场离婚风波中彻底失了势
然而亨利八世也不是一个宽厚仁爱的君主
《狼厅》第1季 第1集
沃尔西 给我滚出来
Wolsey, you're out!
诺尔福克勋爵 萨尔福克勋爵
My Lords Norfolk and Suffolk.
红衣大主教 沃尔西阁下
Cardinal Wolsey.
你已经从大法官的职位上被解职了
You're dismissed as Lord Chancellor,
这是国王陛下的直接命令
by the King's orders.
请立即归还大法官的印玺
You're to return to us the Great Seal.
你是说你们在举行晚宴？
You'll have supper?
你就是迷恋这掌控一切的感觉 对吗
You wanted all to rule yourself, didn't you?
然后把所有的勋爵们像小学生一样的管教 在这里苦苦挣扎是吗
and had the lords like schoolboys, creeping in here.
现在 我就在这
Well, I am here now...
而且 我要生吞了你
..and I will chew you up.
把你生吞活剥 骨肉分离
Bones, flesh and gristle.
现在立刻交出大法官的印玺！
You're to hand over the Great Seal.
呵
Ah!
很显然 如果你能给我一张国王陛下亲手写的辞呈也是极好的
Apparently, a written request from the King is necessary.
你们随身带着了吗？
Do you have one?
没有吗？
No?
噢 那可真是粗心呢
Oh, that's careless.
这位是我的律师 托马斯・克伦威尔
My lawyer, Thomas Cromwell.
你想让我们就为了一张纸就再骑马从这里往返温莎一次？
You want us to ride back to Windsor for a piece of paper?
在这种恶劣的天气下？
In this weather?
是呀是呀
I see, yes.
事实上 我的律师告诉我 我不能交出我的印玺
Actually, my lawyer tells me I can't give you the Seal,
无论你们有没有国王的辞呈
written request or no.
确切的说 他告诉我的是
He tells me that, properly speaking,
我的印玺只能交还给主记事官阁下
I should hand it only to the Master of the Rolls.
所以说呢...
So...
你们回程的时候最好带着他一起来这里
you'd better come back with him.
很荣幸见到你 大法官阁下
I'm obliged, master.
你说的那些是事实 还是自己胡编的？
Did you know that, or did you make it up?
估计他们一天内就会反应过来了
They'll be back in a day.
唉 现在这动乱的日子
Well, these days,
能争取24个小时已经是天大的胜利了一样
24 hours feels like a victory.
有没有给我们的客人招待茶点呢？
Do we have refreshments for our guests?
用什么招待？连盘子都被没收了
Served on what? They've taken the plate.
你穿的这是什么？
What's this?
我借来的
It's borrowed.
他们查抄了我的整个衣橱
They've confiscated my wardrobe
你也知道的 我很怕冷
and you know how I feel the cold.
谢谢你了 彼得
Thank you, Peter.
我想这座大房子会被赏给安妮・博林吧
This is to be Anne Boleyn's, I think.
国王陛下想让她在伦敦有个住所
The King wants her to have a London residence.
这座宫殿是归约克主教区所有的
This palace belongs to the Archdiocese of York.
那安妮夫人什么时候成为的大主教？
When did Lady Anne become an Archbishop?
别这样说 托马斯 我所拥有的这一切 都是国王陛下赏赐的
Now, now, Thomas. Everything I have, I have from the King.
如果他想要这座约克宫殿 那就完好无损的给他
If he wants to take York Place, fully furnished,
我们再另寻一处避身之所好了
then I'm sure we'll find some other roof to shelter under.
他一直都觉得我家里有一座
He's expecting to find a wax figure of himself
上面插着针的他的蜡像
with a pin stuck through it.
你跟我过来
Come and see me.
给我个理由 勋爵大人
Why, My Lord?
什么时候？
When?
等你再注意一点你的礼节
When you've mended your manners.
你们这是在干嘛 在服侍王子吗
What it is, to serve a prince.
基督教世界里最宽厚最睿智的王子吗
The gentlest, wisest prince in Christendom.
我以后将再也听不到任何人敢说出反对亨利国王的言语了
I'll not hear a word against Henry from any man.
你觉得这一切只是英国人才会这样做吗
Do you think it's something about the English?
他们见不得一个伟人的崛起 所以必须在他崛起前毁灭他？
They cannot see a great man set up, but they have to pull him down?
这不只是英国人如此
It's not the English.
人性本恶
It's just people.
我们将安妮夫人从法国
We brought the Lady Anne back from France,
带回嫁到了爱尔兰
to marry into Ireland.
现在我看到了她正在和年轻的亨利・珀西在假面舞会上尽情欢舞
Now I hear she danced at the court masque with young Harry Percy.
在漆黑的拐角处你侬我侬
Connived in dark corners with him.
我本不应该看见的
And I won't have that.
公爵大人 我真不敢想象我现在正和您在派对上...
Your grace can't think that I'm party to...
噢 托马斯・博林爵士
Oh, Sir Thomas Boleyn.
你应该很惊讶我现在的想法
You'd be amazed at what I can think.
安妮知道和年轻的亨利・珀西的事情不会发展顺利的
Anne knows things can't proceed with young Harry Percy.
但亨利相信自己有权利自由的选择自己的妻子             - 自由？
- But he believes he's free to choose his own wife.  - Free?
选择他的...？
Choose his own...?
他可不是什么随随便便的放牛娃！
He's not some ploughboy!
他未来某一天可是我们这北方的领主啊
He's the man who'll have to hold the north for us, some day.
珀西家族可是涵盖了这片大陆上最尊贵的贵族
The Percy family comprise the noblest in the land,
然而博林家族嘛 却有过一次...
whereas the Boleyns were once in...
什么来着？交易是嘛？
What? Trade, weren't you?
那个人是谁？
Who is that?
是谁？
Who's that?
噢 是斯蒂芬・伽纳德 我的秘书 [后来的温彻斯特主教]
Oh, it's Stephen Gardiner, my Secretary.
让他出去
Send him out.
斯蒂芬
Stephen.
那个人又是谁？！
And who is that?
你别管那么多了 他谁都不是
Never mind who that is. He's nobody.
现在的问题是...
The problem is...
...我的女儿和亨利・珀西
..my daughter and Harry Percy,
我觉得他们现在有点情到深处了
I think they may have gone a little far in the matter.
看起来他们已经私定终身了
It seems they've pledged themselves before witnesses...
这个嘛 你可以完全忽略所有的什么誓言证词
Well, you can forget all talk of pledges and witnesses.
我会马上通知他的父亲从边境赶回来
I'll get his father down from the borders
如果这个败家子竟敢忤逆他父亲的话
and if the prodigal defies his father,
他会被直接剥夺爵位继承权
he'll be tossed out of his heirdom on his prodigal snout.
所以说 早点把你的女儿给嫁到爱尔兰去
Now, get your daughter married into Ireland,
趁她还没听到什么风吹草动之前！
before her intended hears any rumours of spoilt goods.
说完了吗 大主教阁下？
Finished, My Lord Cardinal?
说完了
Finished.
狗娘养的！
Butcher's boy!
狗杂种！
Butcher's dog!
过来呀 狗东西
Come out, dog.
他在和你说话
He's talking to you.
所以 克伦威尔大师
So, Master Cromwell.
威廉・波普利告诉我 你可能会对我有点用处
William Popely tells me I might find a use for you.
他说 你是一个多才多艺的人
A man of many talents, he says.
有着惊人的记忆力?
A remarkable memory?
这是有技巧学成的 勋爵阁下
There's a technique, My Lord.
我是在意大利学会的
I learnt it in Italy.
你在国外呆了多长时间?
How long were you abroad?
12年
12 years.
那你来自哪里?
Where are you from?
帕特尼 离开的时候我还是个小男孩
Putney. Left when I was a boy.
那你父亲呢？
Your father?
是个铁匠
Blacksmith.
哈 终于！
Ah, at last!
一个比我出身更卑微的人！
A man born in a more lowly state than myself.
嘿...
Hey...
- 贝拉!      - 吃了吗?
- Bella!     - Eaten?
- 吃了     - 葡萄酒?
- Mm-hmm.  - Wine?
有何不可?
Why not?
我打算为他工作 那个红衣大主教
I'm going to work for him - the Cardinal.
你知道他们在意大利怎么说吗?
You know what they say in Italy?
"王子必须做出选择"
"II principe bisogna sceglierlo."
-"你必须选择你自己的王子"           - 做什么事?
- "You have to pick your prince."   - Doing what?
任何他想要的
Whatever he wants.
我们有的已经足够多了
We have enough.
我不想把我的一生浪费在买卖这些交通工具上 莉兹
I don't want to spend my life dealing in conveyances, Liz.
不管这个男人的围墙应该在这里或这里...
Whether this man's fence should be here or here...
我想你应该知道你自己在做什么
You know what you're doing, I suppose.
至少 你总是看起来好像你知道自己在做什么
At least, you always look as if you do.
是的 我就是这样 不是吗?
Yeah, I do, don't I?
你看起来比那个红衣大主教要甜美的多
You're sweeter to look at than the Cardinal.
这可算得上是一个女人所能收到的最差劲的恭维话了
That's the smallest compliment a woman ever received.
我们的儿子说了什么?
What does our son say?
他说...希望你一切都好 希望我一切都好
He...hopes you are well, hopes I am well,
希望他可爱的小妹妹们安妮和格雷丝都很好
hopes his lovely little sisters Anne and Grace are well.
他自己也很好
He is well.
‘就写到这里 没什么时间了 你孝顺的儿子 格雷戈里’
‘And now no more, for lack of time, your dutiful son, Gregory.’
字好丑的拉丁文
Terrible Latin.
安妮才是更出色的学者
Anne's the better scholar.
安妮 去吃早餐吧
Anne, go and get your breakfast.
学完拉丁语 我想学一学希腊语
After I've Latin, I'd like to learn Greek.
格雷戈里几乎都不会说一句希腊话
Gregory has hardly any Greek.
要是这种人当上市长了 伦敦得变成什么样子?
What will London be like when that one's Lord Mayor?
这是德国寄来的
From Germany.
它被包装成其他样子 我几乎把送信的男孩赶走
It came packaged as something else. I almost sent the boy away.
- 如果你想知道...          - 我不想知道
- If you want to know...   - I don't want to know.
..这是廷代尔翻译的《新约全书》 莉兹
..it's Tyndale's New Testament, Liz.
你应该自己读读它
You should read it for yourself.
它是英文翻译版 这才是重点
It's in English - that's the point.
不是拉丁文的
Not Latin.
基督教怎么会是误认为异教！
How can that be heresy?
读读它 你将发现你是如何被误导的
Read it and you'll see how you're misled.
没有提到修女 僧侣 文物...
No mention of nuns, monks, relics...
没有提到教皇
No mention of Popes.
我的祈祷书对我来说就很好了
My prayer book's good reading for me.
你的祈祷书?
Your prayer book?
格雷丝 看看这个
Grace, look at this.
理夫?
Rafe?
理查德?
Richard?
噢...
Oh...
- 你迟到了        - 我迟到了 还是你的自我感觉太良好了
- Late.           - Me, or your good self?
- 当然是你      - 他正在里面等你
- You           - he's waiting.
我的船夫们都喝醉了
The boatmen were drunk.
我真惊讶你居然自己没有带把桨
I'm surprised you didn't take an oar yourself.
你在河边长大的 不是吗?
You grew up at the river, didn't you?
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
谢谢你了!
Thanks!
噢 国王今早给我来了封信
Oh, the King sent for me this morning
非常非常早的时候
exceptionally early.
他想要做什么？
What did he want?
主的怜惜
Pity.
和一个儿子
A son.
国王想要一个儿子
The King wants a son.
18年的婚姻 却一直没有子嗣继承人
18 years of marriage, with no heir.
他决定有一些罪孽必须实现 来破除这个诅咒
He's decided some sin must have been committed, to cause this curse.
噢 上帝...
Oh, God...
你这是从哪学来的?
Where did you learn this?
在码头上 我离开家后不久
At the docks, a little after I left home.
有一段时间 我就靠它维持生计了
Earned a living from it, for a while.
所有人都觉得他们怎么也不会输给一个孩子
Everyone thought they could beat a child.
我还需要进一步了解
What else should I know about you,
一个可怕的仆人?
monstrous servant?
有一次在意大利 我拿一条蛇做赌注
Once, in Italy, I held a snake for a bet.
它有毒吗?
Was it poisonous?
我们不知道 这个就是赌点
We didn't know - that was the point of the bet.
罪过吗?
The sin?
噢 是的 罪过
Oh, yes, the sin.
我还记得当年他们把凯瑟琳皇后从西班牙带回来的时候
I remember when they brought the Queen over from Spain
把她嫁给了亨利的哥哥 亚瑟王子
to marry Henry's brother, Prince Arthur.
那年她才16岁
16...
真的是言语难以形容
barely a word of English.
上帝 当她跳舞的时候...
God, when she danced...
...她红色的头发滑过她的肩...
...her red hair slid over her shoulder...
那上帝原谅你了吗?
God forgive you?
主会宽恕世间所有的罪恶
God forgive us all.
后来 亚瑟王子去世
Then Arthur dies,
亨利决定与自己的寡嫂结婚
Henry decides he'll have his brother's widow for himself.
凯瑟琳也坚自己仍是处子之身
Katherine declares that she's still a virgin,
可怜的亚瑟 从未得到过她
poor Arthur never having touched her.
罗马方面也发出了豁免令
Rome issues the dispensation
与此同时 任何提出异议的人都...(灭口...)
and any doubts anyone has...
可是如今呢？
But now?
不错  如今 王后还是不能产下王储
Well, now, the Queen can't give the King a son.
所以 也就是说
So, now...
王后当年根本不可能是处子之身
..the Queen must not have been a virgin, after all.
亨利说这些年他都是活在不合法的婚姻关系里
Henry says that he's lived all these years in an unlawful marriage.
全都是罪孽
Hence the sin.
所以 要请求罗马教廷 正式废除这段婚姻
So it's back to Rome, for an annulment.
当然了 凯瑟琳会十分怨恨我
She's blaming me, of course - Katherine.
因为她自然是不能怨恨国王的 那就都由我承担吧
She can't blame the king, so it's all my doing.
不论我怎么乞求他不要这么离婚 都于事无补
No matter that I've begged him not to proceed.
作战击败苏格兰的时候 我听说她想把
When she defeated the Scots, I heard she wanted to send
苏格兰国王的人头砍下献给亨利
the Scottish King's head in a bag to Henry,
以此来取悦他
to cheer him up.
怎么 我觉得她是真正的巾帼英雄
Well, she's a fighter.
哈！
Ha!
或许你现在应该教教我怎么玩这个捉皇后的小把戏
Perhaps you should teach me your three-card trick, hmm?
说不准我们哪一天也会流落街头呢！
In case we both end up on the streets!
伙计们 快把东西都卸下来  给我点引火料 快点 干的引火料
Unpack everything. Masters, I want kindling, dry kindling.
史蒂芬 快生火 然后找找厨房在哪儿
Get the fires lit. Stephen, find the kitchen.
不 还是先照顾主教要紧 我要人给他铺床寝用具
Actually, see him in first. I need the bedding.
那个谁  迈克吗？ 下来  快点  等会儿再管马
What... Who is that? Michael? Down, off. The horses, later.
我要主教大人马上能躺在暖和的床上
We want the Cardinal in bed and warm.
加油 麻利点 抓紧时间
Come on, come on, we're not done yet!
我刚才问他们有没有肉豆蔻或是藏红花
I asked if they had nutmeg or saffron
他们都用疑惑的眼神看着我 好像我说的是希腊语
they looked at me as if I was speaking Greek.
我不得不找到当地的供货商
I'll have to find a local supplier.
我真该祈祷一下 希望自己能找到
I shall pray for it.
而与此同时 我却正在为国王及他的顾命大臣们祈祷
Currently, I pray for the King and all his counsellors.
为凯瑟琳王后祈祷 和安妮夫人祈祷
I pray for Queen Katherine and Lady Anne.
为同样深深怨恨我的托马斯・莫尔祈祷
I pray for Thomas More, who hates me so.
为国家的风调雨顺
I pray for a better harvest
以及 人民的丰衣足食 而祈祷
and that the rains might stop.
我为万事万物而祈祷
I pray for everyone and everything.
此时此刻 只有在我对上帝祷告说
It's only when I say to the Lord...
‘现在 轮到托马斯・克伦威尔...’
"Now, about Thomas Cromwell..."
上帝却对我说
..does God say to me,
沃尔西 难道你不懂什么事适可而止吗？
"Wolsey, don't you know when to give up?"
来 让我代替上帝祝福你
Let me... Let me bless you.
这是他们期盼已久的
This is what they've waited for
萨尔福克 诺尔福克  博林
Suffolk, Norfolk, Boleyn.
我不死 他们是不会善罢甘休的
They won't rest until they have my head.
托马斯 你现在应该离我而去
You should leave me, Thomas.
就像伽纳德那样
Gardiner has.
卑鄙小人当然会
Gardiner would.
汤姆
Tom?
一路平安到家
Safe journey home.
我准备走了
I'm going to leave.
他说他会送我去安妮夫人那里
He says he'll send me to the Lady Anne.
我觉得她会赏识我的 对吗？
I think she'll like me well enough, don't you?
留在这里 还有什么意义呢
What's the point of staying here?
他们都会慢慢厌倦那个老头儿的
They're going to be rid of the old man.
这是大势所趋
It serves him right.
那克伦威尔呢？
And Cromwell?
那个律师?  就让他和那个老头一起自生自灭去吧
The lawyer? He'll go down with him.
额... 要我说 不过就是个所谓的律师而已
Well... I say, "lawyer" -
天知道他到底是个什么东西？
who knows what he is?
要不是那个老头的话
He comes from nothing.
他现在还只是一无所有的贱民
The old man brings him in
这才不过几年光景 还真以为自己是个人物了
and in a few years, it's as if he's the one in charge...
以为自己接替红衣主教的权利 继续作威作福了吗
..as if he has some hold over the Cardinal.
我听说他在国外杀了人 至今还是戴罪之身呢
I heard he killed a man abroad and never made confession.
但这种人...
But that kind...
一看到刽子手 只会以泪洗面
they always weep when they see the hangman.
是的 确实是我邀请你的 但是...
I did, but...
只不过发生了这么多事 我以为你会陪着沃尔西的
..with things the way they are with Wolsey, I thought...
托马斯 莫尔也来了
Thomas More is here.
看起来你也邀请了他
Well, I expect you invited him too.
- 格雷西亚    - 普雷戈
- Gracia.     - Prego.
莫尔先生 你有什么想对我说的吗？
Did you want to talk about me, Master More?
趁我在这儿 你有话可以当面对我说 没事儿 我脸皮厚
You can speak while I'm here, I have a thick skin.
没人想要跟你谈
No-one was talking of you.
那么 要说红衣主教什么呢?
Of the Cardinal, then?
托马斯 这位是查普伊先生
Thomas, this is Monsieur Chapuys,
新一任的驻英大使
the Emperor's new ambassador here in London.
查普伊先生 这是我的朋友 托马斯 克伦威尔
Monsieur Chapuys, my friend, Thomas Cromwell.
很高兴认识你
Enchanted.
其实我自己也不知道我是哪冒出来的
I hardly know where I come from, myself.
如果您不想让我听懂你们的谈话
If you want to speak half-secretly,
那就请你们用说希腊语吧  查普伊先生
try Greek, Monsieur Chapuys.
先生  如果您不待见他的话 就想象自己在看一条鲱鱼吧
My friend, you are looking at your herring as if you hate it.
- 鲱鱼也没什么不好                          - 哈哈哈
- There's nothing wrong with the herring.   - Ah.
说到红衣主教沃尔西 不得不提的是
But of Cardinal Wolsey, I'll say only this
他这辈子算是完了
he has brought his fall on himself.
自取灭亡罢了   土地 金钱 头衔
He's drawn all to himself - land, money and titles.
他总有统治众人的野心
He's always had a greed for ruling over other men.
但红衣主教到底还是个公众人物
The Cardinal's a public man.
你愿意帮他从这个惹眼的位置上退下来吗
Would you have him shrink from a public role?
可是 现在为时已晚了
Well, I think it's a little late
就让他在那潮湿的小屋里受点教训吧
to read the Cardinal a lesson in humility.
他的好朋友们早就警告过他了 但他都置若罔闻
His real friends have read it long ago and been ignored.
那你觉得你是真正的朋友吗?
And you count yourself a real friend, do you?
我当然会告诉他的 以基督的名义 大法官阁下
I'll tell him - and by the blood of Christ, Lord Chancellor,
当他被流放的时候 他会找到自己的慰藉
he'll find it a consolation as he sits in exile
并且疑惑为什么你会去国王那儿诽谤他
and wonders why you slander him to the King.
- 先生们...    - 不 我们直说吧
- Gentlemen... - No, let's have this straight.
汤姆斯说 ‘如果我可以选择的话 我会在教堂里度过余生
Thomas here says, ‘I'd spend my life in the church, if I had a choice.
我醉心于精神世界
I'm devoted to things of the spirit.
视钱财为身外之物
I care nothing for wealth.
世人的评价对我如过眼云烟’
The world's esteem is nothing to me.’
所以这就是我回到伦敦
So how is it I come back to London
然后发现你已经成为尊贵的大法官的原因吗?
and find you've become Lord Chancellor?
尊贵的大法官
Lord Chancellor.
这算什么?
What's that?
是他妈的意外吗?
A fucking accident?
你对教堂来说可不是个朋友 托马斯
You're no friend to the church, Thomas.
你只是一个神父的朋友而已
You're a friend to one priest only
而且还是基督世界里最腐败的神父
and he's the most corrupt in Christendom.
你一定得给我制作这个酱汁的菜谱
You must give me the recipe for this sauce.
托马斯・莫尔是我的老朋友
Thomas More is my old friend.
你不该来这儿折磨他
You shouldn't come here to bait him.
那我就不是你朋友吗 伯尼斯?
Am I not your friend too, Bonvisi?
你很清楚你是的
You know you are.
这也是为什么我给你这个建议
And that's why I give you this advice.
红衣大主教已经完蛋了
The Cardinal is finished.
他迟早会离开的
He'll go.
接着你就没有主家保护你了
And then you will be without a master to protect you.
现在就离开他
Leave him now.
你觉得是真的吗
Do you think it's true?
他犯的错是因为太自负
The mistake was being too proud?
我记得他以前经常说
I remember when he used to say,
‘国王会做这些 做那些'
"The King will do such and such."
后来变成 ‘我们应该做这些 做那些’
And then it was, "We will do such-and-such."
现在变成 "这是我要做的"
Now, it's "This is what I will do."
不 不
No, no.
真正的错误 是树立了一个安妮・博林这样的敌人
The mistake was making an enemy of Anne Boleyn.
不过呢 谁能知道她会走多远呢?
But then, who knew how far she'd rise?
托马斯!
Thomas!
主人 有从罗马传来的最新消息
Of course, master. News from Rome.
罗马皇帝的军队已经攻进城内了
The Emperor's troops have run wild in the city.
他们正到处杀人 强奸妇女...
They're killing, raping...
托马斯・莫尔说他们把婴儿放在火上烤的劈啪作响
Thomas More says they're roasting babies on spits.
不过士兵们根本没时间吃 他们在忙着偷东西
Soldiers don't have time to eat babies. They're too busy stealing.
如果查理大帝一会儿让他们吃的话
If the Emperor Charles had paid them once in a while...
他们已经俘虏了教皇
They've taken the Pope prisoner.
你说什么?
What?
罗马皇帝是王后的侄子
The Emperor is the Queen's nephew.
如果他抓到了教皇 那国王离婚的那个请求就...
If he has the Pope, then the King's divorce petition is...
是啊...
Yeah...
每次有紧急情况
In every emergency,
都看看是不是能给你的王子找到些什么可利用的帮助 托马斯
look to see if there's some advantage for your prince, Thomas.
啊 樱桃
Ah, cherries.
我该怎么办呢 我想问
How did I do that, I wonder?
来，拿着
Here, take.
但现在 在现在这个紧急情况中
Now, in this current emergency,
对我来说 克莱门特教皇 现在看起来就像是...
it will be to me that Pope Clement looks to...
好吧 是为了让所有基督国家团结在一起的 存在
well, keep Christendom together.
因此 假设我到法国去
So, suppose if I were to travel to France
在议会中把所有的红衣主教们叫到一起 你知道的
and gather together the cardinals in a council, you know,
在教皇出缺的这期间管理教堂的事务?
to conduct the business of the church in the Pope's absence?
现在 如果教堂的事务...
Now, if this business...
碰巧包含国王的私事的话
happened to include the King's private matter...
我们能不对它进行裁决吗?
might we not rule on it?
而且 你瞧瞧
And voila,
英格兰国王变成了单身汉
the King of England will be a bachelor.
什么?
What?
没从丝绸商那儿听到更多消息吗?
Not more gossip from the silk merchants?
有流言说国王已经从玛丽・博林那儿搬出来了
Rumour is the King has moved from Mary Boleyn
搬到她那个平胸的妹妹那儿去了
to her flat-chested sister.
安妮?
Anne?
她还没原谅你关于哈里・珀西的事儿呢
She hasn't forgiven you for that business with Harry Percy.
- 好吧...  - 卡文迪什跟我说 她发誓要找你报仇
- Well...  - Cavendish tells me she's sworn vengeance on you.
可怜的黄毛丫头...
Poor chit of a girl.
国王在夏天会和她同床共枕
The King will have her in his bed by summer.
到了秋天 他就厌倦她 打发她离开了
By autumn, he'll tire of her and pension her off.
你在干什么呢？
What are you doing?
为了格雷戈里
For Gregory.
这跟凯瑟琳王后给国王的衬衫是一样的设计
It's the same design Queen Katherine uses for the King's shirts.
好吧 如果我是她的话
Well, if I were her,
我肯定会在衣服上留根针的
I'd leave the needle in.
我知道你会这样做的
I know you would.
你妹妹今天来过了
Your sister was here today.
她又问你能不能去看看他？
She asked again if you'd go and see him?
她说你现在已经不了解他了 他戒了酒 定居下来了
She said you'd hardly know him now. He's stopped drinking, settled down.
格雷丝 亲爱的
Grace, sweetheart,
你要离火炉远点
will you keep away from the fire with those, eh?
这可是你的天使翅膀
They're your angel wings.
它们可是为圣诞节准备的
They're just supposed to be for Christmas.
我知道得
I know.
好了 去玩吧
All right, off you go.
托马斯 你的父亲他
Your own father, Thomas
他从没见过我们的孩子们
and he's never seen the children.
很好啊 继续这样吧
Well, let's keep it that way.
我能选择我想跟谁结婚吗?
Can I choose who I want to marry?
什么?
What?
我能选择我想跟谁结婚吗?
Can I choose who I want to marry?
只要是合乎情理就行
Within reason.
那我选拉夫
Then I choose Rafe.
- 你...
- You...
格雷丝说我不能嫁给他 因为他是我的表亲
Grace says I can't marry him because he's my cousin.
理查德是你的表亲 但拉夫不是
Well, Richard's your cousin, not Rafe.
拉夫是我的护卫
Rafe is my ward.
就是说拉夫的父亲曾请求我带他入行
That means Rafe's father asked me to take him in
在商业环境下把他带大 你明白了吗?
and bring him up in business. Do you understand?
所以我能选拉夫咯?
So I can choose Rafe?
如果他等你的话就能
If he'll wait for you.
拉夫?
Rafe?
她本来会选更糟的选择
She could do worse.
- 我热的睡不着      - 噢
- I'm too warm.     - Oh.
回你的床上去 格雷丝 宝贝
Go back to bed, Grace, sweetheart.
你打算一整晚都带着那对天使翅膀睡觉吗?
Are you going to wear those angel wings all night?
我想祷告完再摘掉
Till I say my prayers.
跟我说你要去哪里
Tell me when you're going.
莉兹 我哪也不去
Liz, I'm not going.
沃尔西不在 我是不会去法国的 记得么?
I'm not going to France with Wolsey, remember?
回床上继续睡吧 莉兹
Go back to bed, Liz.
- 你好 佛朗西斯     - 先生
- Hello, Francis.   - Sir.
如果有人找我 就说我不在
Anyone asks for me, I'm not here.
好的 克伦威尔大人
Yes, Master Cromwell.
圣经的语言对我来说就像蜜糖
The words of the scripture are as honey to me.
我沉醉在上帝的话语中
I am drunk on the word of God.
我读过廷代尔的《新约福音》
I've read Tyndale's gospel.
人群 禁食 守夜
Masses, fasting, vigils,
赦免于炼狱
pardons out of purgatory...
所有这些都是无用的
all useless.
所有的这些让我明白
This is revealed to me.
上帝啊 老兄 你真以为你这德行能逃过主的圣裁吗
For Christ's sake, man, do you think you can crawl out of your hole
就因为红衣大主教沃尔西阁下走了?
because Cardinal Wolsey is away?
这一切意味着伽纳德和莫尔
All that means is that Gardiner and More
将会有更多的空闲来追捕我们
have a free hand to pursue us,
把我们打成异教徒
to brand us heretics.
只有沃尔西能保护我们
Wolsey protects us.
沃尔西?
Wolsey?
沃尔西烧了他的圣经
Wolsey burns bibles.
可莫尔可是会烧死异教徒的
More will burn men.
我在德国见到了廷代尔
I met with Tyndale in Germany...
噢 我...
Oh, I...
我可不想知道廷代尔在哪
I don't want to know where Tyndale is.
先生们...
Gentlemen...
我打算去罗马 去见教皇
I'm going to go to Rome and see His Holiness.
我知道的 我可以让他用我们的方式来思考的
I know I can bring him over to our way of thinking.
这是怎么回事?
What is it?
快说！
Say it.
她...
She...
今早你离开以后她说她很累
She said she was tired this morning, after you left.
她什么也不吃 然后...
She wouldn't eat anything, then...
她就开始发抖
she started shaking.
两点左右 我们叫来了牧师
We called for the priest around two.
她说她在意大利抓过一条蛇
She said she held a snake in Italy,
但是牧师说那只是她发烧了 在说胡话
but the priest said that was just the fever talking.
他看起来就像迫不及待要走
He couldn't wait to get away.
她有没有...嗯...
Did she, er...
她留了什么口信吗?
Did she leave any message?
有没有给我的?
For me?
她只是不停地说口渴
Just kept saying she was thirsty.
姑娘们出事了
It's the girls.
坚持住 坚持住!
Come on, come on!
拜托 坚持住!
看着我 拜托 拜托 醒醒 亲爱的
Stay with me. Come on, come on, wake up, darling.
拜托 拜托 你能听见我说话吗 亲爱的?
Come on, come on. Can you hear me, darling?
你能听见我吗? 拜托
Can you hear me? Come on.
坚持住 请坚持住...
Come on, please, please...
醒醒 把眼睛睁开
Wake up, open your eyes.
快睁开眼睛 亲爱的
Open your eyes, please, darling.
拜托...
Please, come on...
快 坚持住 拜托...
Come on, come on, come on, please...
拜托 睁开眼睛 亲爱的 拜托 拜托...
Please, open your eyes, darling, come on, come on...
不要 不要合上眼
Don't, don't.
-拜托...不要...拜托...
- Please...come on...No...Please...
让她们安然离去吧 给她们怜悯慈悲吧...
Mercy, mercy, mercy...
不要这样...
Don't.
没事的...
It's all right.
去吧...安心去吧...
Go. Go now.
人人都说它回来了
Everybody said it was back.
这种...
This...
..汗热病   [亦称 流行性粟粒疹热]
..sweating sickness.
我应该让她们去乡下的
I should have sent them to the country.
莉兹不会让她们走的
Liz wouldn't have let them go.
你每次离开 安妮都会哭
Anne cried every time you were away.
是吗?
Did she?
安妮哭过?
Anne did?
约翰和我会跟你在一起待一段时间
John and I can stay with you for a while.
料理家务 直到你...
Look after the household, until you're...
安妮她曾经想学希腊语
She wanted to learn Greek.
嘿...
Hey...
噢...呃...
Oh! Ugh!
你去哪了?
Where've you been?
你看起来就像个外国人
You look like a foreigner.
我本来就是个外国人
I am a foreigner.
你要去哪?
Where'd you go?
没有目的地 随便走走
Here and there.
上次我听说 你现在为沃尔西卖命了
Working for Wolsey now, I hear.
我是名律师
I'm a lawyer.
律师？
Lawyer?
你不过只是夸夸其谈而已
You were always a talker.
耍嘴皮子功夫 是救不了你的命的
Slap in the mouth couldn't cure you.
上帝知道你已经尽力了
God knows you tried.
法律？
Law?
如果不是因为有法律 我早就是一名勋爵大人了
If it wasn't for the law, I'd be a lord.
克伦威尔有钱
Cromwells had money.
我们有地
We had estates.
真是多了了你们律师
Thieved off us -
把我们的地都给夺走
by lawyers.
我我知道你不会承认这些的 不是吗？
Suppose you don't admit to me, now, do you?
估计你心里早就希望我死了千遍万遍了吧
Suppose you hoped I'd be dead.
你为什么会在这儿
Why are you here?
我妻子让我来见见你
My wife told me I should come see you.
现在你见到了
Well, now you have.
是
Yeah.
什么事？
What is it?
主人 我想问您个问题
Master, I have a question to put to you.
我父亲去世了 现在
My father is dead and you...
你就是我父亲了
You are my father now.
所以我应该改跟着你的姓氏吗？
So, shall I change my name to yours?
你父亲？
Your father?
我每天都在为他祈祷
Every day I light a candle for him.
那你心里有好些吗？
Does that comfort you?
说实话我不知道
I don't know.
不过...
Well, this...
这让我释怀了许多
This comforts me.
你的名字现在是 理查德・克伦威尔
Richard Cromwell.
谢谢您
Thank you.
- 如果...  - 走 走吧 下去吧 快走
- If...    - Go, go on, get out. Get out.
嗯...
Ugh!
啊！
Agh! Oh!
快给我起来！
Now, get up!
起来！
Get up!
来啊，小子！让我看看你有多少能耐！
Come on, boy! Let me see you stand on your feet!
起来！
Get up!
- 啊！     - 给我起来！
- Agh!     - Get up!
Get...up!
起...来！
你应该听说了国王陛下对我的款待有多棒了
You'll hear the King's reception of me was cool.
虽然说是有点夸张
It's only partly true.
但我的这次任务仍不能说是
Still, my mission could not be described
一个举足轻重般的胜利
as an over-whelming success.
红衣主教们不肯见我
The cardinals wouldn't meet me.
说是到南方去太热了
They said it was too hot to travel south.
所以...接下来怎么办呢？
So...what next?
一个新计划 一个宗教法庭
A new plan. A Legatine Court.
我们要让教皇以他名义派遣特使来
We ask the Pope to send his envoy to act in his name
治理英格兰
and rule here in England,
并确保国王陛下和凯瑟琳的婚姻自始至终
on the validity of the King's marriage to Katherine.
嗯？哈？
Hm? Huh?
呃...
Er...
当你在法国的时候...
When you were in France...
我的妻子和女儿们都相继去世了
..my wife and daughters died.
噢 汤姆...
Oh, Tom...
因主所爱...
Whom the Lord loveth...
克伦威尔大师？
Master Cromwell?
托马斯・克伦威尔 竟然在看祈祷书？
Thomas Cromwell, reading a prayer book?
那么我知道事情的严重性了
Now I know how bad things are.
他怎么样了？
How is he?
你离开后...
He asks after you...
他马上就问起你
the minute you've gone.
担心你在路上摔下来
Worries you'll fall in the road.
乔治 你有约克宫殿这的财产清单吗
Have you an inventory for York Place, George?
什么？
What?
约克宫殿 我要送给她
York Place. I'll take it to her.
送给安妮夫人？
To the Lady Anne?
嗯哼
Mm-hmm.
马克？
Well, Mark?
你在用功学习呢
You're hard at study.
你还好吗？
How are you?
回到约克宫殿这让你感到陌生了吧
It must feel strange, being back at York Place -
毕竟世界变化莫测
with the world so altered?
没有
No.
你不想念红衣大主教阁下吗？
You don't miss My Lord Cardinal?
不想
No.
好吧 你可能不愿想起我们
Well, you might not think of us, Mark, but...
但我们仍会挂念你
we think of you.
为什么！别让我的小不点跑掉
Pourquoi! Don't let him out!
安妮夫人
Lady Anne.
您可真客气
Vous etes gentil.
那好
Allors...
克伦威尔
Master...
大人？
Cremuel?
你把这里的清单带来了吗?
You have your inventories?
可真是多谢了你的慷慨
Thank you for this.
自从红衣大主教阁下风光不再后
Since My Lord Cardinal's reduction,
我想您过得还不错吧？
have you seen much progress in your cause?
在英格兰 他是唯一能满足你所需的人
He's the only man in England who can obtain for you what you need.
很好
Very well.
继续为他说话  你有五分钟
Make his case. You have five minutes.
如果不是的 你应该会很忙才对
Otherwise, I can see you're really busy.
红衣大主教是唯一有权利从教皇那里接过国王王后离婚判决的人
The Cardinal's the only man who can deliver an annulment from the Pope.
也是唯一能够拯救陛下良知
He's the only man who can deliver the King's conscience -
甚至让陛下完全醒悟过来的人
and deliver it clean.
如果国王想要得到那份判决的话
If the King wants it
并且按照你所说的 红衣大主教
and according to you, the Cardinal,
这位前任王国统治下的主教 也想要它
formerly the chief subject of the kingdom, wants it...
那我不得不说 克伦威尔大人
Then I must say, Master Cremuel
这还真是花了很久很久的时间才得以实现啊
it's all taking a marvellous long while to come to pass.
而且凯瑟琳王后已经不再年轻了
And she's not getting any younger.
没有人比我们的红衣大主教更紧张了吧
No-one is more distressed than the Cardinal
国王得不到他内心所求的欲望
that the King cannot have his heart's desire,
因为这同时也是红衣大主教内心的欲望
which is ever the Cardinal's desire too.
因为他知道国王所有统治下的国民
He knows that all the King's subjects
- 都把他们的希望寄托在你身上 希望你能诞下王位的继承人...   - 很好
- repose their hopes in you, for an heir to the throne...  - Very nice.
很好！克伦威尔大人
Very nice, Master Cremuel.
有本事你再说一遍！
But try again.
有一件事！
One thing.
我们要求红衣大主教做的就这么一件简单的事情而已
One simple thing we asked of the Cardinal
- 但他却坚决不会去做   - 你知道那并不是简单的事
- and he would not.    - You know it wasn't simple.
好吧 也许因为我只是一个普通的人
Well, perhaps I am a simple person.
你觉得我是么?
Do you feel I am?
也许吧 但我对你了解的并不多
You may be. I hardly know you.
你该走了
You may go.
玛丽夫人
Lady Mary.
我的天 我还以为她会狠狠扇你一耳光呢
God, I thought she would slap you.
我妹妹天性比较好斗
My sister likes a good fight.
下次再来试试吧
Come again.
我已经迫不及待了!
I can't wait!
我认为你姐姐能行的
Your sister can, I think.
噢 她知道该如何等待的
Oh, she knows how to wait.
据我所知
So I hear.
他们说她和国王...
They say she and the King...
还在藕断丝连着 这是真的
..still haven't. It's true.
她让国王为她倾倒 并亲吻她的胸脯
She lets him pull down her shift and kiss her breasts.
男人一样可以 如果他能找到的话
Good man, if he can find them.
玛丽夫人 安妮夫人找你
Lady Mary, Lady Anne wants you.
噢 我的天!
Oh, by the saints!
我要再次申请 在议会中取得一个席位
I need a seat in Parliament again.
为什么?
Why?
因为如果我不在那边为主教阁下说话
Because if I'm not there to speak for the Cardinal,
他们会马上杀了他
they'll kill him.
克伦威尔 我会满足你的愿望 让你在成为议会的议员
Cromwell, I am content you are a burgess in the Parliament.
谢勋爵大人
My Lord.
我也和国王说了 他也同意了
I spoke to the King for you and he is also content.
你会在下议院中接收到他和我的指令
You will take his instructions in the Commons - and mine.
大人 两道指令是一样的么?
Will they be the same, My Lord?
你这该死的 克伦威尔...
God damn it, Cromwell...
你为什么总是要表现成这样的...
Why are you such a...
一个人呢?
person?
就好像你能承担的起你这么做的后果一样！
It's not as if you can afford to be.
就这样一笑置之吧!
Smile away!
国王会授予你一个听众席位的
The King will grant you an audience,
但他已经准备好和你斗法了 大师
but he is preparing a quarrel against you, master.
噢 对了
Oh, yes!
他记忆力十分出色 而且记得非常清楚
He has a long memory and well remembers
在你上一次当选议员的时候
when you were a burgess in the Parliament before this -
你是怎样反对他挑起的战争的
and how you spoke against his war.
我至今仍希望他不要再想着了侵略法国
I hope he doesn't think still of invading France.
你去死吧! 有哪个英国人不这么想
God damn you! What Englishman doesn't?
法国那地方本来就是我们所有的!
We own France!
我们有权去夺回属于我们自己的东西!
We have a right to take back our own!
你给我听着...
Mind you...
也许你说的没错
You're right.
也许我们打不赢这场战争
We can't win.
但无论如何我们必须要去战斗
But we have to fight anyway.
这就是为什么说沃尔西犯了错
That was what was wrong with Wolsey
他总是想着如何谈判签协议
always at the treaty table.
一个屠夫的孩子怎么会懂...
How can a butcher's son understand...
拿戈卢?    [产自波尔多地区的高级红酒]
La gloire?
你难道是屠夫的儿子吗?
Are you a butcher's son?
铁匠的儿子
Blacksmith's.
你认真的?
Are you really?
给马打蹄铁的那种?
Shoe a horse?
如果我再刻苦专精一点的话 但我曾经是名战士
If I were put to it - I was a soldier, myself.
是么?
Were you?
我敢说 你在任何的英国军队里都不够格
Not with any English army, I'll be bound.
我知道你是有些地方很不讨我喜欢
I knew there was something about you that I didn't like,
但我绝对不会对你指指点点
but I couldn't put my finger on it.
说说 你当时是在哪?
Where were you?
加里格利亚诺
Garigliano.
和谁一起?
With?
- 法国人         - 呵！
- The French.    - Huh!
- 你站错队了 少年       - 我知道
- Wrong side, lad.      - I noticed.
那你会用长弓射箭么?
Longbow-man?
偶尔 但玩的不是很好
Now and then. Bit on the short side.
我也是
Me too.
国王可以拉一个满弓
The King can draw a bow.
那很厉害
Very nice.
够得到手臂
Got the arm.
勋爵大人
My Lord,
埃莎尔那里不适合红衣大主教阁下
Esher is not suitable for My Lord Cardinal.
他很愿意前往他在温彻斯特那里的宫殿
He's willing to travel to his palace at Winchester.
噢 我打赌他肯定愿意
Oh, I bet he is.
想的很美 又能很接近国王!
Nice and close to the King!
但别把我们当傻瓜
Don't take us for fools.
告诉你的主教阁下 他和他所谓的法庭
Tell your cardinal that he had his last chance, with his court,
这是他们的最后一次机会！
here in this very building!
告诉他逃到北边去
Tell him to go north.
他没有准备好去北方那边
He's not ready to go north.
我想让他去北方那边
I want him north.
告诉他 诺尔福克想让他快点上路 早早离开这里
Tell him, Norfolk wants him on the road and away from here...
..并且告诉他...
..and tell him...
..如果他不愿意
..if he doesn't,
我会去找他
I'll come to him
然后我将用我的牙齿把他撕裂
and I'll tear him with my teeth.
大人 我能把‘撕裂’替代成‘咬’吗?
My Lord, may I substitute the word "bite" for "tear"?
没什么可替代的 你...
Substitute nothing, you...
..你这个无名小卒
..you nobody.
20年来
For 20 years,
我一直都陪在你身边 是你真正的爱妻
I have been your true wife.
我们一起生育了很多个孩子
And by me, you have had many children...
...虽然上帝很宠爱他们 把他们从这个世界上带走
...although it pleased God to call them from this world
但这并不是我的过错
which was no fault of mine.
当你第一次拥有了我
And when you had me first -
上帝为我作证 我是个真正的处子之身
as God is my witness, I was a true maid,
从没有碰过男人
without touch of man.
不管你承认与否
And whether this is true or no,
这答案只有你自己的良心知道
I put to your conscience.
在亚瑟王子的新婚之夜 我和牛津伯爵
On Prince Arthur's wedding night, myself and the Earl of Oxford
将王子带到了凯瑟琳王后的寝宫
took the prince to Queen Katherine's chambers
当他爬上床在她旁边时 我们都站在那里
and we were there when he climbed into bed beside her.
第二天早上 他再次出现 说他很口渴
Next morning, he comes out again, says he's thirsty
并要一些啤酒 因为 他说
and asks for some ale, because, he said...
"昨晚我身在西班牙！"
"Last night I was in Spain!"
你们都知道 女王是西班牙人呀
The Queen was Spanish, you see?
那是个多么可怜的新郎官啊
It would be a poor sort of bridegroom
谁会在大早晨就出来并且说
who'd come out in the morning and say,
"多么好的一天 大师 我们什么也没做成"
"Good day, masters. Nothing done!"
他才15岁 他在吹嘘自己呀
He was 15, he was boasting.
我宁愿相信凯瑟琳王后
I believe Katherine.
不要相信任何人
Believe nobody.
你迟到了 斯蒂芬 他们这一天几乎都耗光了
You're late, Stephen. They're almost done for the day.
无所谓
It doesn't matter.
为什么无所谓?
Why doesn't it matter?
我从我的一个在罗马的手下听到了一个消息
News from one of my men in Rome.
克莱门特教皇 正准备和罗马皇帝签署一个条约
Pope Clement is preparing to sign a treaty with the Emperor.
噢...
Oh...
这男孩不懂你说的什么意思
Your boy doesn't understand.
罗马皇帝是不会轻易接受教皇的帮助
The Emperor won't take kindly to the Pope helping
来让她姑姑放弃王位的
to have his aunt cast off the throne.
我不认为教皇的特使在那里
I don't think your papal envoy in there
是想给国王他最想要的 你觉得呢?
is likely to give the King what he wants, do you?
但如果他真的给了国王最想要的
And when he doesn't,
那么沃尔西就会完蛋了
Wolsey will be finished.
然后我也会将为你感到十分遗憾
And then I'll feel sorry for you.
除非你不会这样
Except you won't.
对 除非我不会这样
Except I won't.
克伦威尔? 你的那个胖牧师怎么样?
Cromwell? How's your fat priest?
他怎么样了...?
How is...?
他不会好的 除非他得到殿下您的青睐
He cannot be well till he has Your Majesty's favour.
指控他罪名的名单每天都在增加
The list of charges against him grows every day.
殿下 每个人都已经有了答案
Saving Your Majesty, there's an answer to each one
给他一个听证会的机会吧 我们会成功的
and given a hearing, we'd make them.
不是今天
Not today.
萨尔福克今天想去打猎
Suffolk wants to go hunting.
我们通常说 我们这些绅士们 狩猎是为将来的战争做准备
We usually say, we gentlemen, that the hunt prepares us for war.
这给我们带来很棘手的一点 克伦威尔大师
Which brings us to a sticky point, Master Cromwell.
是的 确实是
It does, indeed.
你说 在议会上 一次演讲中 大约六年前
You said, in Parliament, in a speech, some six years ago,
说我承受不了一场战争
that I could not afford a war.
战争是我们买不起的东西
Wars are not affordable things.
然后当我进入法国
When I went into France,
我围堵在了一个镇上的Therouanne 你管这叫...
I captured the town of Therouanne, which you called...
- 一个狗洞 殿下          - 你怎么这么肯定的?
- A dog-hole, Majesty.   - How could you say so?
呃...我去过那
Er... I've been there.
我也是 还是统领一支军队前去
So have I - at the head of an army!
是你说我 不能领导我自己的军队!
You told me I could not lead my own troops!
是你告诉我 如果我被俘虏了
You told me if I was taken prisoner,
赎金将使国家破产! 所以 你到底想要干什么?
the ransom would bankrupt the country! So, what do you want?
你想让国王蜷缩在王宫内 像一个生病的小女孩儿?
You want a king to huddle indoors, like a sick girl?
那样状况也许会很理想 只站在财政的角度上看
That would be ideal, for fiscal purposes.
一名身体强壮的男人 行动起来却会被处处受制
A strong man acts within that which constrains him.
我问你 是什么在限制我?
What constrains me?
是距离
Distance.
当殿下的祖先在法国作战时
When Your Majesty's ancestors fought in France,
他们攻下了一整个省
they held whole provinces.
在那里 他们可以自给自足粮饷军备
From there, they could supply, they could provision.
可现在我们却只有加来一个城市而已
Now we have only Calais,
打起仗来 我们要如何才能供给一支在敌人内部的军队呢?
how can we support an army in the interior?
所以下次我们再去法国时
So next time we go into France,
一定一定需要一个海岸做供给点
we'll need a sea coast.
- 当然 比如诺曼底, 布列塔尼半岛
- Of course.Normandy, Brittany.
克伦威尔大师
Master Cromwell,
你的名声可不是很好
your reputation is bad.
你难道不要为自己辩护吗?
You don't defend yourself?
殿下可以自己构成自己的观点
Your Majesty can form your own opinions.
是 我可以
I can.
而且 我也会的
I will.
我们现在画出穿着大衣的红衣大主教的手臂了吗?
Are we to paint out the Cardinal's coat of arms?
不行
No.
再涂一遍
Paint it again.
涂得颜色再亮点
Paint it brighter.
彼以国士待我，我以国士待之，用过免费优质字幕服务，
而又有能力的人，有义务将这个免费服务做下去若有心加入我们 联系：dajiazimuzu@163.com